Guide to the Stanford University, Assistant to the President for Black Affairs, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Assistant to the President for Black Affairs, records
1968-1973
SC0154
Stanford University. Assistant to the President for Black Affairs.
4.5 Linear feet
The records of the office of James E. Simmons under its several titles includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, general material on black affairs at Stanford and some additional files on Native American students. Also includes Simmons' 1973 report to the President.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, Dean of Student Affairs Office, 1977.
Information about Access
Access to some materials restricted; for more information, contact the archivist.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
In 1968, Stanford University created the new office of Assistant Provost for Minority Affairs, naming James E. Simmons to the post; in 1969, Mr. Simmon's title was changed to Assistant to the President for Black Affairs. The office developed and supported educational, economic, and social activities of black Stanford students, faculty and staff on campus and in East Palo Alto, and worked with the Black Student Union. Convinced of the necessity to integrate the needs and concerns of blacks at Stanford with other minority groups and seeing more staff and faculty resources for black students on campus, Simmons recommended the discontinuation of a separate Black Affairs Office in 1973 and the redeployment of its services to the Dean of Student Affairs, the Office of Financial Aids and the Graduate Division.
Description of the Collection
The records of the office of James E. Simmons under its several titles includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, general material on black affairs at Stanford and some additional files on Native American students. Also includes Simmons' 1973 report to the President.
Arrangement
Office files by subject.
Access Terms
Simmons, James E.; Stanford University. Assistant Provost for Minority Affairs.; Stanford University. Assistant to the President for Black Affairs.; Stanford University. Black Student Union.; Stanford University. Dean of Student Affairs.; Stanford University. Office of the President; Affirmative action.; Minorities--Blacks.; Minorities--Native Americans.; Student aid.; Student employment.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Academic Council, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Council - Committee on Undergraduate Admissions & Financial Aids, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Council - Committee on Undergraduate Admissions & Financial Aids, 1971-73 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Information Center, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Activity Codes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Admission Information, 1969-73 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Advisee Information, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Advisees - Simmons (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Affirmative Action - Memos & Reports, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Affirmative Action, Committee on - Minority Affairs, 1971-73 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Association - Correspondence, 1968-72 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Indian Students - Correspondence, 1968-71 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Indian Students - American Indian Project, 1969-72 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Indian Students - Inter-Tribal Council of California, Inc., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Indian Students - United Native Americans, Inc., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - American Indian Students - U.S. Dept. of the Interior, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Assembly, California Legislature, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Benefits - Staff, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Black History Week, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Black Students Medical Program, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - BSEC - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - BSU [Black Student Union] Film Festival, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - CAPER [Conmdttee on Athletics & Physical Education], 1970-73 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Carbon Copies, 1968-69 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Carbon Copies - Bob, 1968-69 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Carbon Copies, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Churches - Correspondence, 1969-70 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chicano Orientation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Civil Rights Material, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Claire Harrison Associates - Publicity & Public Relations, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - College Day Activities, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Colleges - Correspondence, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, n.d. [IBM dictaphone letter to Dr. Glaser; letter to Gregory Morris] (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Counselling and Testing Center - Correspondence, carbon copies, 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Counselling and Testing Center - Staff - DuPraw, Virginia, 1966-70 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Credit Union - Correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Dawson, Michael Crosby, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dean of Students, 1970-73 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - East Palo Alto Space (1627 Bay Rd.), 1969-70 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Education, 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Educational Associates Inc., 1968-72 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Elliott, Mrs./Cater, Johnson, Price, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Employment, Dept. of, 1969-73 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Employment Minorities Committee, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Program, 1967-72 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Evening Outlook, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fair Play Council, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial Aids - Correspondence, 1968-73 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Five-Year Project, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Focus, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Foreign Visitors, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Foundation News, 1969-72 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Freshman Seminars 1 & 3 (JDB), 1971, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fundraising/BSVC, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Motors Corp., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - GSO [Gen. Secy's. Office], Carbon Copies, 1968-73 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Graduate Student Association, ASSU, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Health, Education & Welfare, Dept. of, 1969-71 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - High Schools, Correspondence, 1968-71 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Incoming (Bob), 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Institute for Applied Behavorial Science, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Joe's Correspondence [Joseph Goone], 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Martin Luther King Fund, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Masters, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Memorandums, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Memorandums, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Memorandums, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Mexican-American, 1968-72 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Mid-Peninsula Citizens for Fair Housing, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Minority Employment Commission, 1969-71 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Minority Employment Program, 1967-72 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Minority Group Recruiting Reports, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Minority Students Program, 1968-71 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miss Watts Summer Festival, 1971-72 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Movements, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Multicultural Exhibit, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Nairobi College, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Nairobi Schools, 1970-72 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Urban League, Inc. - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Olympic Fund - Rischa Williams, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - OICW (Opportunities Industrialization Center West), 1969-72 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Overseas Campus Lists, 1969-72 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pact, Inc. - Educational Clearinghouse, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Palo Alto-Stanford Resources and Needs/Ad Hoc Committee, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Personnel - Correspondence, 1969-73 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Petty Cash, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Physical Facilities, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Pre-Med. Information & Proposal, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Pre-Med. Society, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - President's Office Staff Meeting - Minutes, 1969-73 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Private Schools - Correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Provost Communication - Carbon Copies, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Provost's Office - Correspondence Folder #1, 1968-73 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Provost's Office - Correspondence Folder #2, 1968-73 (Box 2, Folder 52a)
  - Questionnaires (Incoming & Outgoing), 1969-72 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Report: "The Black Conummity of Stanford - a Review", by J. Simmons, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Report to President Lyman, 1973 Apr 20 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reports, 1969-71 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Requirements - Petroleum Engineering, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Residence Declarations (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Residence Hall Staff, 1968-70 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Resumes, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - ROTC Material, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - SC 5 - Masters ["Meaning of death in Western culture"], Summer 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scholarships Clearance Comission, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Scholarships, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - School of Education - R & D Center, 1970-72 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Search Committee Dean/Engineering, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Search Conmittee for Asst. to the President for Mexican-American Affairs, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Senior Week Activities, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Soledad Group [The Stanford-Soledad Teaching Project], Folder #1, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Soledad Group [The Stanford-Soledad Teaching Project], Folder #2, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 18a)
  - Spector, David Lawrence [empty] (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Staff Notifications. [empty] (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The Stanford Coaching Camp (Information), 1970-71 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Stanford in Washington, 1972-73 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Stanford Tutorial Program, 1969-71 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Student Financial Aid, Sub-Committee on, 1970 Feb 4 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Student Financial Aid, 1970 Jul 3 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Study of Graduate Education at Stanford (SES) - Recommendations and Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Summer Work & Study Program, 1969-70 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Task Force - Correspondence, 1970-72 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Task Force - Charges, 1969-70 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Task Force - Evaluation Sheets, Summer Work and Study, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Task Force - Tutorial Expenditures (E. Grady McGonagill), 1969-70 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Telegrams - Outgoing, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Transfer Cooperative Program, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Tutorial Program - Carbon Copies, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Undergraduate Education, Committee on, 1969-72 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Undergraduate and Graduate Studies, 1972-73 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - United Campus Christian Ministry at Stanford, 1969-71 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - United Scholarship Service News, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - U.S. Information Agency, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Universities, Correspondence from, 1969-72 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - University Governance, 1968 Oct 3 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Upward Bound Program, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - URS Systems Corp., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Veterans Administration, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Visiting Black Scholars Program, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Watoto Project Program, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - The Winner, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Work/Study Programs, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Wright Institute, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Youth Opportunity Program, 1967-71 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Youth Opportunity Program, 1972-73 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Youth Opportunity Program - Recruiting Information, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 56)
LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS
BAADASSS - Black Athlete's Academic Development Association by Stanford Student Service
BAP - Budget Adjustment Program
CAPER - Committee on Athletics and Physical Education
CRUD - Committee on New Undergraduate Living Ideas [?]
CUS - Committee on Undergraduate Studies
SES - Study of Education at Stanford
SGES - Study of Graduate Education at Stanford
YOP - Youth Opportunity Program